<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bytepawn - Coding</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/coding.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-02-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Cloud9: Cloud coding that actually works</title><link href="/cloud9.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-02-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Marton Trencseni</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-02-07:/cloud9.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 2 months I've been using Cloud9 for writing code in the cloud, and I can wholeheartedly recommend it: it just works for me. It's basically Docker plus an IDE: you get a Docker container running Ubuntu that you can access over a web IDE.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've always wondered when it will be practical to write code in the cloud (and not locally).
Most of the apps I use have already moved to the cloud: email, calendar, docs, music. Writing code is one of the last blockers to a true thin client approach for me (the other notable one being photo management).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been using &lt;a href="https://c9.io"&gt;Cloud9&lt;/a&gt; for writing code in the cloud, and I can wholeheartedly recommend it: it just works for me. It's basically &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; plus an IDE: you get a Docker container running Ubuntu that you can access over a web IDE. Docker is a pretty standard thing, so there's not much to say there. The good news is that there's also not much to say about the IDE: &lt;strong&gt;it just works&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can theme it, I have it set up to look and feel like Sublime. It has a nice treeview on the left, you can do simple file management there. Shortcuts like copy/paste, find, etc. work as expected, as does full-text search. It's quite impressive, I've been using it for about 2 months and I haven't run into a single instance where the webapp/javascripts feeling leaks through. Part of the IDE is the ability to open terminal consoles. Like the editing, the terminal also just works, including copy/paste, shortcuts, and so on. The one use-case I found where the IDE doesn't work is over mobile: trying to use it over a touch interface is horrible. They're working on it and this will get better over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some screenshots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/images/c9-1.png"&gt;Editing a Markdown file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/images/c9-2.png"&gt;Terminal console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one problem I kept hitting is that I'm used to Cmd-Tab'ing to get to Sublime, but if it's running in Chrome it's a tab window. I couldn't get used to that. So I used &lt;a href="https://www.lessannoyingcrm.com/blog/2010/08/149/Create+application+shortcuts+in+Google+Chrome+on+a+Mac"&gt;this shell script&lt;/a&gt; to create a dedicated Cloud9 Chromium app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The container is accessible from the outside, so if you launch a webserver on localhost:8080, you can open it from your browser at https://&lt;project&gt;-&lt;username&gt;.c9users.io. At first I thought this is public so anybody can see it, but they check whether you're logged into c9, so actually only you can see it---nice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://c9.io/pricing/webide"&gt;business model&lt;/a&gt; is freemium. In the free tier can run 1 private docker container (with 1G space); you can launch more, but they will be public, meaning anybody can see your files. For $20/month you get unlimited private containers, and 10G disks (see &lt;a href="https://docs.c9.io/docs/reaching-resource-limits"&gt;reaching resource limits&lt;/a&gt;). I've been using the free tier, right now I'm at 50% disk usage. Most of it is stuff I install to get something working (&lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;pip install&lt;/code&gt;, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also enables a nice "separation of concerns": you can work on your personal projects on a computer (eg. work computer) without storing any files on it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="coding"></category><category term="ide"></category><category term="c9"></category></entry></feed>