<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bytepawn - General</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/general.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Personal goaling</title><link href="/personal-goaling.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Marton Trencseni</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-12-22:/personal-goaling.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The meta-goal of goaling is to stretch yourself to achieve more, and to feel good about what you’ve achieved. Whatever happened this year, it’s always possible to achieve a lot more and feel better about yourself next year. To hijack a Feynman quote, &lt;em&gt;there is plenty of room at the top&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;img src="/images/run2019_1.PNG" alt="2019 running" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using a system of setting and tracking personal goals for the last 3 years. For me, this way has worked out well, so I’m sharing it here. This is not meant to be prescriptive (“do this”), it’s descriptive (“this worked for me”). Here is my &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1J_eay8axCVOTZ9gDk8wLiI3cdI5Qx4r_u318YTOsFg8/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;2019 master goaling doc&lt;/a&gt;, shown inline at the bottom of the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The meta-goal of goaling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meta-goal of goaling is to stretch yourself to achieve more, and to feel good about what you’ve achieved. Whatever happened this year, it’s always possible to achieve a lot more and feel better about yourself next year. To hijack a Feynman quote, &lt;em&gt;there is plenty of room at the top&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More is better&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that having lots of goals is fun. Life has multiple arenas: family, fitness, savings, projects, work, traveling, reading, writing, etc. I try to write down multiple goals for each arena, usually about 5 each. In the end, my complete list of goals is usually 2 pages of bullets and sub-bullets in a Google Doc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;50/50 goaling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something I learned while working at Facebook. There the philosophy was that goaling should be aggressive; on average you should hit 50% of your goals (or, 50% of teams should hit their goals). When I set my goals at the beginning of the year, I usually think “I’d be happy to hit 50% of these”, but then I usually end up hitting a bit more, like 60-70%. This always reminds me that there is so much more room to stretch and do more. Very few people are near their capacity, I am definitely not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use colors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a Google Doc to write down the goals as bullet points (like “run 1000km”), and separate Google Sheets to track my daily progress towards the goal. I use red, green and orange colors: green when I accomplished what I needed to that day to hit the goal, or when I hit the goal, orange for a missed day, and red if the verdict is out and I missed the goal. These colors carry strong psychological connotation and put pressure---the good kind of pressure---on me to hit my goals. Looking at green is pleasant, green means good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/track2019.png" alt="2019 goals" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Visualize numeric goals on charts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For numeric goals (for me, this is fitness related goals) I use a Google Spreadsheet. The master tab has a daily log of activities. One row is one calendar day; if I didn’t do anything that day, it’s orange. If I did, it’s green. Separate tabs show various line charts, showing my progress as I track toward my yearly goal. Charts are another type of visualization that have a strong psychological effect on me in terms of motivating me to get the line to move up and to the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/run2019_1.PNG" alt="2019 goals" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Show the goal line&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For goals such as "run 1000km", where I continuously make progress, I break it into a daily goal (1000/365 km per day), and show that goal line on the chart. This is another strong visual cue that motivates me, I have to follow the goal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Look at the goals daily&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goaling only works if you care about the goals. The best way to do that is to look at the goals all the time. I have 3 tabs (one master Google Doc, one Google Spreadsheet for fitness and one Google Spreadsheet for financials) pinned open in Chrome, and look at them daily. I always know how I’m tracking towards my goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set cumulative goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find setting cumulative goals like “run 1000km in 2019” works much better for me compared to weekly goals like “run 20km per week in 2019”. The problem with the weekly version is, what happens if you miss your goal on one week? Have you already missed the yearly goal? How many weeks are you allowed to misss? Setting a cumulative goal like “run 1000km in 2019” is great, because it becomes a game: if I don’t go running on a week, no problem, but I’ll have to make it up the following weeks. And knowing that making up is tough, I don’t miss my weekly targets unless there’s a good reason (like illness).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set S and L goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s not clear what the right goal is. Should the target be 500km or 1,000km of running? When I don’t know what the realistic goal is, I set a S and an L goal. Some time down the line I will see if the S goal is too easy of if the L goal is too hard, and focus on hitting the right one. If I decide to hit the S goal, I keep the L goal on the list (marked in red); it’ll be a good stretch goal for next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set realistic goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you set unrealistic goals, you will know deep down that you will never hit your goals, or it is very unlikely. If you’re unsure what’s realistic, set S and L goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Break your goals into H1 and H2 goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your goal is to run 1,000km in a year, break it down into a 500km goal for H1 (Half 1), and an overall goal of 1,000km for H2. This way, when you hit the 500 km sub-goal in June, you can green it out and feel good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Renegotiate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are personal goals. The meta-goal of goaling is to stretch yourself to do more, and feel good about it on the way. But there's no point to feeling bad about not hitting an unrealistic goal. If you’re some months into the year, and you realize that a goal was too ambitious, it’s okay to re-label it as an L goal and introduce an S goal. Also, sometimes circumstances change (new job, new city, family), and goals become unrealistic; in that case, it’s okay to renegotiate the goal with yourself, and introduce a new, different, better fitting goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use leading metrics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are leading metrics and lagging metrics. A leading metric is about something actionable today, like going running or cutting calorie intake. A lagging metric is the outcome of the leading metric, like “80kg body mass”. I set my goals as leading metrics, because they can be translated to something I will do daily, and I can keep track of my gradual progress. Also, I find goals like “lose 10kg” poor, because what happens once I lose 10kg? Suppose I lose it by September? Am I done with my yearly goal? If I just gain it back, that’s a fleeting accomplishment. I find it better to set leading metrics goals, which can be translated to daily actions and weekly cadence, ie. routine. It’s easier to maintain your weight if you’re used to running and working out a lot and controlling your calorie intake, and if you feel bad if you miss a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Should be up to you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals should be up to you, so "get promoted" is not a good personal goal, because it's not up to you: the company could have a bad year, you could get a new manager, etc. Instead, figure out what are the best things you can do to get promoted ("land 4 big features", "mentor 2 juniors", "present at 2 conferences", "organize an offsite") and write those down. A good goal is one where you can feel bad if you didn't hit and blame it on not trying hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Track secondary metrics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondary metrics are, for example, "% active days" for your activities, or the location split of your running kilometers. Since you're tracking your metrics anyway, these are easy to split and visualize and can give you interesting insights ("wow, I do most of my running indoors").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/runloc2019.png" alt="2019 running" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;External commitments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;External commitments, created on purpose by you, can be a great tool for hitting your goals. Simply go around and tell everybody what your goal is. For example, in 2008 I decided to do an Ironman. I gave myself a year to prepare, and in that year I told everybody I met I'm going to do an Ironman. There was no way I could go back on it, I told everybody!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dopamine hits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using daily tracking, colors and cumulative goals (eg. running kilometers accumulate like gold in an RTS game) already gives you a dopamine hit every time you do something and update your tracking. You can get an additional hit if you post about it on Facebook. I think there is social good in this, because it may motivate others to also go out and do something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sample goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1J_eay8axCVOTZ9gDk8wLiI3cdI5Qx4r_u318YTOsFg8/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;My 2019 master goaling doc&lt;/a&gt;, after redactions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://docs.google.com/document/d/e/2PACX-1vQn49UZbLT-v88d6qu1ojz1dsz2bfhAW0C0DdZDIKBmYHMl1ApycI9a4_3McXCr4MfnBsQ4ZyzYArmu/pub?embedded=true" style="width: 1000px; height: 800px;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="self help"></category><category term="goaling"></category></entry><entry><title>What not to spend time on</title><link href="/what-not-to-spend-time-on.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Marton Trencseni</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-07-23:/what-not-to-spend-time-on.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffett says deciding what &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to spend time on is just as important as deciding what to spend time on.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;img src="/images/warren-buffett.jpg" alt="Warren Buffett" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I read &lt;a href="http://www.euclidean.com/the-essays-of-warren-buffett-review-lessons-quotes/"&gt;Warren Buffett's books&lt;/a&gt; and some stories about him. One of the lessons stuck with me, it's something I think about regularly when deciding what to spend time on. Below is an excerpt from &lt;a href="https://jamesclear.com/buffett-focus"&gt;James Clear's website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The story of Mike Flint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Flint was Buffett's personal airplane pilot for 10 years. (Flint has also flown four US Presidents, so I think we can safely say he is good at his job.) According to Flint, he was talking about his career priorities with Buffett when his boss asked the pilot to go through a 3-step exercise. Here's how it works…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Buffett started by asking Flint to write down his top 25 career goals. So, Flint took some time and wrote them down. (Note: you could also complete this exercise with goals for a shorter timeline. For example, write down the top 25 things you want to accomplish this week.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Then, Buffett asked Flint to review his list and circle his top 5 goals. Again, Flint took some time, made his way through the list, and eventually decided on his 5 most important goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 3:&lt;/strong&gt; At this point, Flint had two lists. The 5 items he had circled were &lt;strong&gt;List A&lt;/strong&gt; and the 20 items he had not circled were &lt;strong&gt;List B&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flint confirmed that he would start working on his top 5 goals right away. And that's when Buffett asked him about the second list, &lt;em&gt;“And what about the ones you didn't circle?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/warren-buffett.jpg" alt="Warren Buffett" style="width: 600px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flint replied, &lt;em&gt;“Well, the top 5 are my primary focus, but the other 20 come in a close second. They are still important so I’ll work on those intermittently as I see fit. They are not as urgent, but I still plan to give them a dedicated effort.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which Buffett replied, &lt;em&gt;“No. You’ve got it wrong, Mike. Everything you didn’t circle just became your Avoid-At-All-Cost list. No matter what, these things get no attention from you until you’ve succeeded with your top 5.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I don't spend time on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is great advice, it's something I think about regularly. I will list 2 things here that I decided not to spend time on after reading this Warren Buffett bit a few yeas ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quantum Field Theory&lt;/strong&gt; (and research-level physics in general). I have a degree in Physics, it's a second degree I got mostly for fun and curiousity. Getting it has been one of the greatest decisions of my life, learning and doing Physics has been continually paying off ever since than, both personally and for work (Computer Science + Physics = Data Science). As a physicist you learn the deep insights of your predecessors, but also that with certainty they are wrong in some sense, and over time their achievements will be "just" an approximation or a special case. So physicists are always learning and adjusting their perspective. Physicists also have a keen sense for measurements, statistics, errors, which is very useful when dealing with numbers in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after I got the Msc degree in Physics back in 2008, I started a Phd that I never finished because I went off to do a startup. Maybe it's because I never finished it, but for many years afterwards, I had this romantic notion and kept going back to Physics in my free time, reading papers, books. I once even had a yearly goal of writing a paper and submitting it to a journal. I actually did it, I wrote a short paper titled &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1208.4990"&gt;Pure Lattice Gauge Theory in the Expanding Universe&lt;/a&gt;, and submitted it to the Physical Review Letters (PRL), but got rejected (most papers get rejected at first, &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; scientists keep improving and submitting). Since I don't &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; care about getting into a journal, I didn't spend any more time on it, now it just sits on Arxiv [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when I decided not to spend time on Physics anymore, it was not a trivial thing to do. I really like to do Physics, even in my spare time. But at the end of the day, I'm not in Academia, so I don't actually have time to follow topic(s) of research like real scientists do and figure out how to contribute. Also, academia is pretty crowded, and research topics have become very specialized. It's not really a good investment of time for me; investing my time into things related to software/startups has much higher potential impact and payoff. I also stopped reading Physics blogs, all the drama around string theory is fun but ultimately just a distraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haskell.&lt;/strong&gt; I first came into contact with Haskell in 2013 when working at Prezi. There are a lot of things that are intesting about Haskell: it's a strongly typed, purely functional language with type classes, type inference, etc. You can do really cool things with Haskell, or so it seems at first. In 2013, before systems like &lt;a href="http://bytepawn.com/fetchr-airflow.html#fetchr-airflow"&gt;Airflow&lt;/a&gt; were opensourced by Airbnb, there was no good standard open source ETL system; but we needed one at Prezi, to replace the bash hairball we had. We used this project as a testing ground for Haskell, and wrote an ETL framework in Haskell (I think we called it Datapipe). We spent about 3-6 months on it and it was a big disappointment. Although we put it into production at one point, it was quickly replaced by a re-write (this time in Go, which I believe is still in production). At a later point I tried using Haskell for a personal project for representing Physics equations and quantities, and also ran into major/deep problems (oddly, I found it easier to model what I wanted with C++ templates of all things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all these failures, I continued to be interested in Haskell. Although I adopted a critical stance, and usually argued against it in conversations, I assumed &lt;em&gt;"it's just me, I don't "get it"&lt;/em&gt;. But I never found or really saw good reasons and generalizable examples where using Haskell in production really made sense. So when I read the Warren Buffett bit, I knew that Haskell is one of those things that I have to stop spending time on, it's just not a practical thing for me to use. I share &lt;a href="http://functionaltalks.org/2013/08/26/john-carmack-thoughts-on-haskell/"&gt;John Carmack's stance&lt;/a&gt;, he views Haskell as a good source for ideas to use in imperative languages like C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think spending time reading/writing Physics papers or Haskell has been a waste for me. Far from it. I learned a lot doing these things. But I've also determined that investing more time into them is not worth it right now. Remembering Warren Buffett and his pilot is a great way to remind myself to stick to it, and spend time on other, potentially more impactful things [2].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] A &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1405.6665"&gt;PRD paper&lt;/a&gt; later referenced it and called it "pioneering work", but I'm pretty sure it's not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Having said that, if I were to go on a sabbatical, doing Physics would be fair game. The point of sabbatical is to take time off from the normal pursuit of things and spend time on more risky/fun projects, in a timeboxed way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="warren"></category><category term="buffett"></category><category term="self"></category><category term="help"></category><category term="physics"></category><category term="haskell"></category></entry></feed>