<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bytepawn - Investing</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/investing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-12-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Warren Buffet style fundamental metrics of long-term company performance</title><link href="/warren-buffet-style-fundamental-metrics-of-long-term-company-performance.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Marton Trencseni</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-12-02:/warren-buffet-style-fundamental-metrics-of-long-term-company-performance.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I look at some fundamental charts of Apple, Activision Blizzard, Intel, Amazon and Fedex.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;img src="/images/aapl_shareholder_wealth.png" alt="AAPL shareholder wealth curve" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years I’ve read a lot of books on investing, especially Warren Buffet-style value investing. I also read Warren Buffet’s yearly investor report. Some relevant links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Intelligent-Investor-Definitive-Investing-Essentials/dp/0060555661"&gt;Benjamin Graham - The Intelligent Investor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Berkshire-Hathaway-Letters-Shareholders-Buffett/dp/0615975070"&gt;Berkshire Hathaway Letters to Shareholders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Security-Analysis-Foreword-Buffett-Editions/dp/0071592539"&gt;Graham, Dodd - Security Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Warren-Buffett-Stock-Portfolio-Investing/dp/1451606486"&gt;Mary Buffett (ex-wife of WB’s son) - The Warren Buffett Stock Portfolio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.stockpup.com"&gt;Stockpup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://warrenbuffettstockportfolio.com"&gt;Warren Buffett : Latest Portfolio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I found some great online resources which give this style of analysis (called fundamental analysis) of companies, and I ended up spending hours browsing company metrics. So here I will show (from these sources) fundamental metrics of publicly traded companies. The point of the exercise is to get a feeling for what these metrics look like for companies in different industries, at different stages of their lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apple (AAPL)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with Apple because Warren Buffett holds AAPL stock himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Cumulative shareholder wealth&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting chart: it shows, per quarter, the book value of the company at the point in time (green), and the cumulative dividends that the company paid out to shareholders up to that point in time (blue). The reason this chart is structured like this is, it says, if you bought 1 piece of AAPL stock in 1994, this is how much “sure money” that 1 stock is worth today. The cumulative dividends are “sure money”, since it’s cash that Apple has given you over the years. And book value is the closest accounting equivalent: it’s total assets minus total liabilities. The total assets can include intangibles like “brand value”, if it was a result of a purchase. One way to think of book value is, this is how much would be left if the company would sold off what it has (including intangibles, with a reasonable assumption of marketability) and paid back liabilities. Note that this chart has nothing to do with the share price of the stock we have to pay on the open market, in 1994 or at a later time. Notice how Apple started paying dividends in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/aapl_shareholder_wealth.png" alt="AAPL shareholder wealth curve" style="width: 650px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="investing"></category><category term="stocks"></category><category term="warren buffett"></category></entry></feed>