<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bytepawn - Self improvement</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/self-improvement.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Personal goaling</title><link href="/personal-goaling.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Marton Trencseni</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-12-22:/personal-goaling.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The meta-goal of goaling is to stretch yourself to achieve more, and to feel good about what you’ve achieved. Whatever happened this year, it’s always possible to achieve a lot more and feel better about yourself next year. To hijack a Feynman quote, &lt;em&gt;there is plenty of room at the top&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;img src="/images/run2019.PNG" alt="2019 running" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using a system of setting and tracking personal goals for the last 3 years. For me, this way has worked out well, so I’m sharing it here. This is definitely not meant to be prescriptive (“do this”), it’s descriptive (“this worked for me”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The meta-goal of goaling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meta-goal of goaling is to stretch yourself to achieve more, and to feel good about what you’ve achieved. Whatever happened this year, it’s always possible to achieve a lot more and feel better about yourself next year. To hijack a Feynman quote, &lt;em&gt;there is plenty of room at the top&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More is better&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that having lots of goals is fun. Life has multiple arenas: family, fitness, savings, projects, work, traveling, reading, writing, etc. I try to write down multiple goals for each arena, usually about 5 each. In the end, my complete list of goals is usually 2 pages of bullets and sub-bullets in a Google Doc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;50/50 goaling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something I learned while working at Facebook. There, the philosophy was that goaling should aggressive; on average you should hit 50% of your goals (or, 50% of teams should hit their goals). I actually think that this is too aggresssive for personal goaling, because if I would feel quite bad if I didn’t half my personal goals, so I lean towards 60/40 goaling. When I set my goals at the beginning of the year, I usually think “I’d be happy to hit half of these”, but then I usually end up hitting a lot more, like 80-90%. This always reminds me that there is so much more room to stretch and do more. Very few people are near their capacity, I am definitely not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use green and red colors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a Google Doc to write down the goals as bullet points (like “run 1000km”), and separate Google Sheets to track my daily progress towards the goal. I use red, green and orange colors: green when I accomplished what I needed to that day to hit the goal, or when I hit the goal, orange for a missed day, and red if the verdict is out and I missed the goal. These colors carry strong psychological connotation and put strong pressure---the good kind of pressure---on me to hit my goals. Looking at green is pleasant, green means good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Visualize numeric goals on a chart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For numeric goals (for me, this is fitness related goals) I use a Google Spreadsheet. The master tab has a daily log of activities. One row is one calendar day; if I didn’t do anything that day, it’s orange. If I did, it’s green. Separate tabs show various line charts, showing my progress as I track toward my yearly goal. Charts are another type of visualization that have a strong psychological effect on me in terms of motivating me to get the line to move up and to the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Look at the goals daily&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goaling only works if you care about the goals. The best way to do that is to look at the goals all the time. I have 3 tabs (one master Google Doc, one Google Spreadsheet for fitness and one Google Spreadsheet for financials) pinned open in Chrome, and look at them daily. I always know how I’m tracking towards my goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set cumulative goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find setting cumulative goals like “run 1000km in 2019” works much better for me compared to weekly goals like “run 20km per week in 2019”. The problem with the weekly version is, what happens if you miss your goal on one week? Have you already missed the yearly goal? How many weeks are you allowed to misss? Setting a cumulative goal like “run 1000km in 2019” is great, because it becomes a game: if I don’t go running on a week, no problem, but I’ll have to make it up the following weeks. And I know that, and I know it’s going to be tough, so I don’t miss my weekly targets unless there’s a good reason (like illness).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set S and L goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s not clear what the right goal is. Should the target be 1,000km or 1,500km of running? When I don’t know what the realistic goal is, I set a S and an L goal. Some time down the line I will see if the S goal is too easy of if the L goal is too hard, and focus on hitting the right one. If I decide to hit the S goal, I keep the L goal on the list (marked in red), it’ll be a good stretch goal for next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set realistic goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you set unrealistic goals, you will know deep down that you will never hit your goals, or it is very unlikely. If you’re unsure what’s realistic, set S and L goals.
Break your goals into H1 and H2 goals
If your goal is to run 1,000km in a year, break it down into a 500km goal for H1 (Half 1), and an overall goal of 1,000 for H2. This way, when you hit the 500 km sub-goal in June, you can green it out and feel good about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Renegotiate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are personal goals. The meta-goal of goaling is to stretch yourself to do more, and feel good about it on the way. If you’re some months into the year, and you realize that a goal was too ambitious, it’s okay to re-label it as an L goal and introduce an S goal. Also, sometimes circumstances change (new job, new city, family), and goals become unrealistic; in that case, it’s okay to renegotiate the goal with yourself, and introduce a new, different, better fitting goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use leading metrics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are leading metrics and lagging metrics. For example, a leading metric is about something actionable today, like going running or cutting calorie intake. A lagging metric is the outcome of the leading metric, like “80kg body mass”. I set my goals as leading metrics, because they can be translated to something I will do daily, and I can keep track of my gradual progress. Also, I find goals like “lose 10kg” poor, because what happens once I lose 10kg? Suppose I lose it by September? If I just gain it back, that’s a fleeting accomplishment. I find it better to set leading metrics goals, which can be translated to daily action and cadence, which then become part of my daily routine. It’s easier to maintain your weight if you’re used to running and working out a lot, and you feel incomplete if you miss a day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="personal-goaling"></category></entry></feed>